In 2015,
A mysterious virus is striking South America.
He was talking about Zika.
the Zika virus.
Hundreds of babies are born with severe mental disabilities.
Once we understood what this virus was capable of,
We became genuinely worried.
This is the untold story of a world war.
There was an army of scientists to fight this virus.
This is how science helped me.
leading the fight against the virus.
And the creature that transmits it.
We remove the tube and inside,
There's this tiny little brain.
We didn't really understand what was happening because it was completely unexpected.
Zika is the new enemy to defeat.
The more we learned,
The more we told each other,
Oh my god,
That's still a surprise.
Early 2015,
Dr. Patricia Brasil sees many women arriving at her clinic in Rio de Janeiro with strange symptoms.
She wasn't doing badly.
She didn't have that appearance that one usually has when one is severely ill.
It was a disease that just gave you a rash and very strong itching.
Dr. Brazil's patients all live in the favelas of Rio.
Irlana Cabral,
aged 19,
is one of them.
Irlana had a slight, barely visible rash.
A redness that disappears in a few days.
We didn't know exactly what it was and we were trying to establish a diagnosis.
But little by little,
Hundreds of thousands of new cases are being reported across Brazil.
The doctors are distraught.
By analyzing the blood of these women,
They detect an unknown virus in South America.
They stumble upon
Zika.
I found a report.
I compared it to what my patients presented.
And I thought to myself,
It's exactly the same thing.
It must be Zika.
Brazilian doctors are not the only ones concerned about Zika.
The first time I heard about Zika,
That was when the new epidemic broke out in Brazil.
That interested me a lot and I wanted to know more about what Zika was like before he reached Brazil.
Anthony Fauci is one of the top medical researchers in the United States.
Even he had to go back into the archives to learn more about Zika.
Zika was first identified in 1947.
but no cases of the disease in humans were observed before 1952.
Afterwards,
in Africa and Asia,
It has more or less disappeared.
The virus was discovered here.
in Uganda,
in the heart of a forest called Zika.
In 60 years,
Only 14 infections have been reported worldwide.
None of them were serious.
Then,
in 2007,
Zika appeared in the Pacific.
on Yap Island.
And in 2013,
in French Polynesia.
We were receiving reports of cases in French Polynesia.
That was before the disease arrived in Brazil.
But in Polynesia,
80%
People who were infected had few or no symptoms.
Everything we learned about Zika suggested that it was an infection without consequences.
In France,
Experts are looking into the Polynesian epidemic and discovering that Zika may not be completely harmless.
During this epidemic,
This was new and had not been seen in Micronesia on the island of Yap a few years earlier.
This involved the onset of severe paralysis in approximately 40-50 patients who had to be hospitalized.
because his paralysis was so severe that he could no longer breathe.
This is what is known as Guillain-Barré syndrome.
Guillain-Barré syndrome is a rare and poorly understood disease that causes a severe attack on the nervous system.
Doctors are surprised by Zika's ability to trigger this syndrome.
But among the infected adults,
Less than one person in a thousand is affected by the disease.
Zika therefore remains an enigma.
We weren't too worried either because we were talking about a few dozen cases.
We became interested in it,
but without being particularly alarmist.
The cases of Guylain Barret in French Polynesia are not reassuring.
But in 2015,
No one yet suspects how dangerous Zika is.
Thousands of babies have been born with brain damage.
Brazil declares a state of emergency.
Laura has microcephaly.
In the fall of 2015,
a few months later,
Hundreds of babies with malformed skulls are being born in Brazil.
They suffer from microcephaly.
A brain development defect that occurs in the early months of pregnancy.
Around the sixth,
tenth week of pregnancy,
The cells that will give rise to the brain begin to multiply.
So if an infection occurs during the first trimester,
in these critical weeks,
The risks that the brain may not develop normally are considerable.
When a baby's head is of normal size,
This is because the developing brain pushes against the skull.
which forms the outline of the skull.
If something disrupts this process,
Then the brain does not develop properly and the skull remains small.
This increase in the number of microcephalic babies is occurring at a time when Zika cases are multiplying.
But is it really the virus that causes the disease?
In Rio,
Panic is spreading among pregnant women.
Including the one followed by Dr. Patricia Brazil.
I was very worried.
The mothers who came for consultations were frightened.
They were haunted by a ghost.
The ghost of microcephaly.
Will my baby be normal?
What will it be like?
Dr. Brazil then performed ultrasounds on all of these patients.
The results are alarming.
29%
The babies of the women presented with malformations.
I was devastated.
I was truly desperate because I put myself in their shoes.
In my opinion,
as a mother,
It's very difficult.
And for them...
Davy,
Irlana's baby...
was born with severe microcephaly.
When my son was born,
It was initially an extraordinary feeling.
That feeling disappeared when I saw all those doctors arrive and take him away.
The doctors tell him that Davy will never develop normally.
I cried so much and I felt so guilty about it.
But maternal feeling,
It's inexplicable.
It's a love that completely engulfs you.
Across Brazil,
Thousands of women are experiencing the same tragedy.
And the cause of microcephaly is still not confirmed.
Blood tests do not always reveal the presence of Zika.
Yet he is the perfect scapegoat.
The problem has reached proportions that are alarming experts worldwide.
The discovery of neurological complications in children took us all by surprise.
And we became genuinely worried.
I remember it very well.
I called an emergency meeting.
I said,
Okay guys,
All hands on deck.
We don't have much time,
Women are infected,
They become pregnant.
Their children are in danger.
We really need to act quickly.
Early 2016,
Scientists around the world are committed to...
Fighting against this epidemic.
They come from different countries and different disciplines.
They must answer three essential questions.
Is Zika really the cause of microcephaly?
How did this initially harmless virus transform into such a formidable enemy?
And finally,
How can we stop this scourge?
Among all these questions,
One thing is certain,
The Zika virus is transmitted by mosquitoes.
When you put a mosquito under a microscope,
We realize that it's a whole world that we have before our eyes.
And we are going deeper and deeper into the functioning of the mosquito to better understand the role of mosquitoes in the transmission of pathogens.
In a secure laboratory in Montpellier,
Frédéric Simard breeds mosquitoes that carry Zika.
This is the species Aedes aegypti,
endowed with an insatiable appetite for human blood.
The mosquito's proboscis is something very mobile.
The mosquito will find the microcapillary where the blood passes using this very small channel.
very, very weak.
Females need blood,
especially for the development of their eggs.
So it is out of maternal instinct that the females bite.
more than for sustenance.
When the female bites,
She injects saliva which thins the blood and allows it to be aspirated more easily.
If the person is already infected with Zika,
the insect...
it sucks in the virus, which then multiplies in its stomach.
Later,
by pricking again,
She injects the virus through her saliva.
infecting its latest victim.
Frédéric Simard is fascinated by these mosquitoes.
His job, however, is to find new ways to exterminate them.
We are going to expose mosquitoes to this insecticide.
The insecticide we use on these mosquito nets is a neurotoxin.
It will attach itself to the mosquito's neurons.
The mosquito will be paralyzed and then die very quickly.
His laboratory is developing new insecticides.
When the first insecticides appeared in the 1940s,
The mosquitoes seem to have been defeated.
The rest of the story will not be so simple.
In 1948,
The WHO declares war on mosquitoes.
The first effective insecticide,
DDT,
is at the heart of this struggle.
We're spraying it everywhere,
hunting down every last mosquito.
To succeed,
every drop of water must be drained or disinfected.
Over vast areas,
including Brazil,
The mosquito has been eradicated.
But the story takes a disastrous turn.
DDT has proven to be toxic to human health.
It was then gradually banned starting in the 1970s.
But above all,
The mosquito has found a way around it.
And the phenomenon will relentlessly repeat itself.
With each new insecticide produced,
Mosquitoes always manage to develop resistance.
A female mosquito will lay eggs
200 to 300 eggs every two days,
This means that this resistance mechanism can very quickly invade an entire mosquito population.
In one month,
A resistant female can produce more than a million offspring.
In 1980,
The Aedes aegypti mosquito is back.
ever more thirsty for conquests and new territories.
Professor Dwayne Goebbler has been tracking mosquitoes around the world for 40 years.
If Aedes aegypti, the mosquito, had the ability to think,
If he could think and reason like us,
I certainly hope he would consider me his number one enemy.
Let's get rid of this guy.
Yet,
retired,
He returned to service upon the announcement of the epidemic.
I would never have imagined it in 1971,
when I started working on mosquito-borne diseases,
that we would be faced,
40 years later,
to an even more serious problem.
Every time I retire,
A new epidemic is coming.
I have to get back in the saddle and return to the fight.
Dwayne Goebbler is monitoring the mosquito's spread in Florida.
More than any other mosquito,
The Aedes mosquito is adapted to living close to humans.
And this behavior makes him a perfect carrier of disease.
Aedes aegypti is a very silent mosquito.
We don't hear it, and generally,
You don't feel its sting.
So if you are in a room with 5 or 6 people and only one Aedes aegypti mosquito,
There's a good chance you'll all get stung.
And if carriers of a virus like Zika,
You will all be infected.
The spread of the Hedes mosquito throughout the world has always been a mystery.
until Dwayne Goebbler helped solve it.
There,
You have the typical breeding site for Aedes aegypti.
He loves tires.
It's an ideal environment for larvae.
Her eggs will hatch and in a few days,
Adults will emerge.
And that's where the problems begin.
Aedes has a weakness for rubber.
It likes to lay its eggs on the inner wall of used tires.
The used tire market is booming.
Each day,
They are loaded by the millions onto cargo ships.
And they crisscross the entire planet.
And the mosquito travels with them.
The tires are shipped worldwide.
They carry the eggs with them.
The eggs hatch and Aedes aegypti mosquitoes are introduced into a new region.
The incredible network of global trade is one of the pillars of our modern society.
But the mosquito has transformed it into a deadly ecosystem.
They have existed for a long time.
much longer than humans.
It is likely that they will still be there when we are gone.
The mosquito has thwarted all of man's attempts to annihilate it.
But grappling with the Zika epidemic,
The Brazilian government had no other choice but to try,
Once again,
to eradicate it.
We are losing the battle against the mosquito.
President Dilma Rousseff declares war on the mosquito.
More than 200,000 soldiers have begun special training.
This time,
The target is not the adult mosquito.
But his descendants.
In the favelas,
The drinking water is infested with mosquito larvae.
A new insecticide is then poured into all the tanks.
But no one is certain that it will be effective.
Then the tension turns towards the root of the problem.
The virus itself.
I live near this lake and I like to come here when I need to rest or find inspiration.
When I first heard about Zika,
I came here to reflect and I asked myself how I could help them.
Ang Lee Tang immigrated from China to the United States to study viruses.
Virology has always interested me.
Viruses are so intelligent,
if effective,
It's fascinating.
When Zika struck Brazil,
His team is working on other mosquito-borne viruses.
He stopped everything to dedicate himself to Zika.
We had the opportunity to stop all our ongoing projects to dedicate ourselves immediately to Zika.
Yes,
I told my team,
Let's go,
Let's try to understand what's going on.
The team wants to one day unravel the mystery of Zika.
But very quickly,
She encounters her first obstacle.
Find enough samples of the virus to study it.
It takes them weeks to obtain them.
Because at the time,
Very few laboratories are working on Zika.
Working with the Zika virus potentially carries risks.
And that worried us.
Because a virus that can cause so much damage to a fetus's brain,
We had never seen anything like it.
What else can it cause?
We wondered what could happen?
What will we discover?
To study Zika,
They need a very large stock of viruses.
They had already developed a rapid way to cultivate other mosquito-borne viruses.
But they have no idea how effective it is against Zika.
The method involves collecting cells from the stomach of a mosquito.
then bathe them in a nutrient liquid where they can multiply.
Then the Zika virus is added, in the hope that it will do its work.
infect existing cells and thus multiply, like in a mosquito.
But will this method work with Zika?
For an entire weekend,
by connecting every 6 hours,
It was necessary to monitor these plaques of cells that contained the Zika virus.
And finally,
We thought we saw something.
So we took the cells,
They were placed under a microscope.
We looked for the virus and we found it.
Henry Tang and his team now have millions of Zika viruses at their disposal to experiment on.
The most urgent question is to discover what happened in the brains of infants.
like little Davy.
Is the virus responsible for microcephaly?
To find out,
Professor Tang needs the help of a neurologist.
It became clear at that moment that I needed to obtain brain cells.
Professor Tang needs very specific brain cells.
Cells that are identical in every way to those in the brain of a fetus.
In 2016,
He doesn't know it yet.
but someone already owns one.
As a scientist,
We are always curious and drawn to mystery.
The first time I saw images of these children born with microcephaly on the news,
I thought to myself,
Maybe I can do something.
Neurologist Go Lee-Ming works with her husband Hong Jung-Sung.
When Zika started to make headlines,
They have just made an extraordinary breakthrough.
They succeeded in creating fetal brains in the laboratory using stem cells.
What's extraordinary about a stem cell,
The reason is that it can be transformed into a heart cell.
in liver cells,
in pancreatic cells and of course in brain cells.
How did they manage it?
They took ordinary human skin cells.
Afterwards,
They genetically reprogrammed them to become stem cells.
They then cultured these cells in a fluid containing exactly the same nutrients that the mother would provide to her fetus for brain development.
The stem cells then develop into thin layers of brain cells.
But they are not satisfied.
because a brain is not just a thin layer of nerve cells.
They need to find a way to make this brain grow in three dimensions.
Which seems completely impossible to them.
But one day,
They have an idea.
They are grown in suspension to make them rotate on their own axis, thus increasing their capacity to absorb oxygen and nutrients.
To grow cells in suspension,
They invent a small machine that rotates the cells without interruption.
Everyone was very enthusiastic.
From now on,
we could develop mini-brains.
Based on their experience,
Go Lim In and Hong Jun Song have prepared new batches of stem cells.
And this time,
They place them in their device.
For many long weeks,
the cells,
practically invisible,
they go and go.
They are growing up,
They finally appear and become tiny globes.
And inside these globes,
They discover something remarkable.
Cells do not just multiply.
They begin to form the complex connections that a fetal brain already possesses at the beginning of pregnancy.
Under the microscope,
Multiple layers can be seen.
We can see the stem cell layer,
the layers of the different neurons.
They form complex structures,
exactly like in a developing human brain.
They function like real nerve cells.
They can send electrical signals to each other,
as they would normally do in the brain.
Go Lim In and Hong Joong Song have therefore succeeded in creating a fetal brain in the laboratory.
Not one.
but hundreds.
Enough to test for the Zika virus.
But for that to happen,
They are still missing a major element.
We started looking for where to obtain the Zika virus.
The only answer we got was that we had to wait several months before the virus became available.
So many scientists are working on Zika that there is now a long waiting list for virus samples.
The two researchers are still unaware that Englitang possesses millions of them.
For the two teams to meet,
A crisis will be necessary.
In March 2016,
A group of environmentalists claims that the authorities are lying to the public about the causes of microcephaly.
Zika is not responsible for this.
he assures.
The virus is a smokescreen.
That's what they want us to believe.
And it has become the biggest fraud in the world.
Zika is not the cause of microcephaly.
They blame the insecticide dumped in large quantities into drinking water in Brazil.
Experts reject this argument.
When you are a scientist,
We shouldn't presume to think we have the right answer from the start.
But we must also be careful not to get distracted by fanciful theories.
That's always how it is in these kinds of cases.
Alternative theories are emerging from all sides.
It had become urgent to know whether the Zika virus caused microcephaly or not.
Because the answer to this question would have a direct impact on public health policies.
As tempers flare,
Ang Lee Tang is desperately trying to find neurologists capable of testing his virus.
A day,
Hong Jun received an email from Ang Lee asking him who was the greatest expert on brain development.
I called him immediately and my first question was, "Do you have the virus on hand?"
And immediately on the phone,
We made the decision to work together.
In just a few days...
The two teams begin their collaboration.
We opened the box and took out the bottles.
Inside,
There were these little clusters of brain cells that were so developed that you could really see the little brains in the tubes.
The experimental protocol is carefully designed.
The result will be decisive.
The virus is then added to half of the small brains.
The other half serves as a control and develops normally.
Will the presence of the virus make a difference?
It's a rather nerve-wracking time because we had to incubate them with the Zika virus and wait for it to develop, and that...
It takes a little time.
Until we saw the effect the Zika virus had on them,
And it was impressive.
The result is indisputable.
and even visible to the naked eye.
The result exceeded all our expectations.
Those who had been exposed to the virus were much smaller.
One week later,
They sent us a photo taken with a mobile phone.
And then,
The result was truly unequivocal.
The Zika virus has been well linked to microcephaly.
because his little brains were much smaller compared to normal brains.
And the infected cells are not just smaller.
Inside,
Scientists are observing the damage caused by Zika.
Once the virus reaches the fetus's brain,
It is capable of attaching itself to developing nerve cells.
The proteins present on the surface of the virus allow it to penetrate to the heart of the cell.
There,
He transforms it into a virus factory.
The cell explodes and dies.
The brain then stops developing.
which leads to microcephaly.
We immediately saw that the layers of neurons were much thinner.
exactly like in babies with microcephaly.
When we saw the images showing how badly the cells could be destroyed,
It was chilling.
Because suddenly,
We have truly grasped the destructive power of this virus.
Work on stem cells
This is a huge turning point in Zika research.
Now,
Scientists are certain that Zika causes microcephaly.
But as the contagion spreads far beyond Brazil,
The news breaks.
Zika virus transmission through sexual contact
a proven case.
A woman living in the capital is believed to have contracted Zika following sexual intercourse.
If a man is infected with Zika...
As we now know that it can be sexually transmitted,
His partner may very well have never been in contact with a mosquito and still be infected.
And this adds a significant risk of...
additional to the Zika equation.
Until Zika,
No mosquito-borne virus was capable of being transmitted sexually.
Then begins,
around the world,
a real race against time to find a solution to the Zika problem.
A vaccine.
More than 20 different groups get to work.
At the heart of their entire project lies a surprisingly simple principle.
A principle invented at the Pasteur Institute,
where the method for creating a vaccine originated more than a century ago.
The idea of ​​the vaccine,
It's about presenting the immune system with components of the virus that will cause the immune system to develop a response.
Vaccines train our immune system to recognize a microbe.
to trigger an immediate response and eliminate it.
To manufacture an effective vaccine,
We need to find the part of the virus that is capable of triggering a massive defense response from our body.
Once identified,
it is in a non-infectious form,
that is to say, something that cannot reproduce in the body,
that the virus element is injected.
During the actual encounter with the virus,
The body is then ready to reject it.
He is vaccinated.
In 2016,
Progress on the Zika vaccine is rapid.
There are already trials today, called phase 1 trials, to see if the vaccine is well tolerated.
There is even a phase 2 trial where they are seeing if it induces an immune response that could be protective.
And that's in humans.
But despite these advances,
Developing a vaccine against Zika presents enormous challenges.
Among other things,
Clinical trials must be conducted on thousands of people.
And they must include women of childbearing age.
We have clearly seen that the main complication of the Zika virus,
These are neurological disorders in children born to mothers infected during pregnancy.
So it is the women,
even before they are old enough to reproduce,
who will be the target of this vaccine.
Testing a vaccine on young girls...
means years of waiting for the results.
And the decision to produce a vaccine on a mass scale also depends on the extent of the epidemic.
In the middle of 2017,
Zika managed to cross the Atlantic to reach the African coast.
one of the most populated regions on the globe.
He returned to his roots.
Will Zika cause an epidemic in Africa?
This is a question that Sarah Salinas attempts to answer.
For her,
The answer lies hidden in the past.
at a time when Zika was already present on the continent,
several decades ago.
But why has no trace of microcephaly ever been found there?
One of the questions scientists have asked is whether the Zika strain has evolved.
compared to the strain originally discovered in Africa,
and had become more toxic.
Sarah Salinas knows that the Zika virus,
which caused the epidemic in Brazil,
is slightly different from the virus found in Africa.
Could this difference explain the danger of the Brazilian virus?
The initial idea was to try to compare this toxicity.
between the African strain and the strain that was also responsible for the epidemic in Brazil.
Early 2017,
The Salinas team already has the Brazilian virus.
But to reconstruct the evolution of Zika,
They need the African virus that was circulating several decades ago.
And the problem,
that's because at the time,
No one was studying Zika.
The search for the African strain continued for months.
Finally,
He's nearing his goal.
He finds a frozen sample of the virus taken in the 1970s in Africa from an infected mosquito.
It really made a big difference because we had access to an African strain that was circulating on that continent.
To test for toxicity...
It manufactures brain cells similar to those used in Baltimore.
Add the old African virus to some of them and the recent Brazilian virus to the others.
Researchers expect the Brazilian strain to attack nerve cells, but not the African virus.
This would explain why there has been no epidemic of microcephaly in Africa despite the presence of Zika.
But what he discovers next takes them by surprise.
The African strain has also infected...
brain cells.
We wondered what was going on,
because those were not at all the expected results.
Actually,
Ultimately,
We were expecting the complete opposite.
SO,
We decided to go further in order to understand what was happening with this African strain.
He repeats the experiment.
But the result is the same.
The African virus is just as infectious as the Brazilian one.
And what's more,
for fetal cells,
It seems to be even more destructive.
The African strain infected nerve system cells much more frequently and was also found to be more toxic.
If the results are confirmed,
It is becoming clear that the Zika virus,
which circulated for decades in Africa,
It also possesses the ability to interrupt brain development.
So why has there been no microcephaly in Africa?
One possible reason could be the development of natural immunity in the African population.
following a very old epidemic.
And the number of microcephaly cases would therefore have fallen rapidly.
What is troubling about microcephaly,
The reason is that it can be caused by many factors.
And the reason why we didn't make the connection with Zika earlier,
This is because Zika existed in an endemic form.
and not in an eruptive form,
That is to say, there was no epidemic.
It is therefore possible that there have been cases of microcephaly linked to Zika.
but they could not be distinguished from microcephaly caused by other causes.
If the Brazilian strain spreads to Africa,
Nobody knows what might happen.
Immune populations,
thanks to the old stump,
Will they be protected against the news?
Nothing is certain.
The mosquito that transmits Zika is everywhere on the continent.
That is why the solutions being considered are radical.
In the city of Piricicaba,
in Brazil...
A new weapon against mosquitoes is being tested.
A day,
It could be deployed worldwide.
We're marking the locations here.
and each time we get closer to a point,
It beeps.
It's time to set them free.
This man is not spraying insecticides.
They release tens of thousands of mosquitoes.
They are released in this area three times a week.
And each time,
That's roughly 250,000 mosquitoes.
These mosquitoes are not ordinary.
They are genetically modified.
And they are on a mission.
This mission begins here.
in the world's largest mosquito factory.
Each week,
100 million insects are produced there.
Carla Tepedino is overseeing the operations.
And she doesn't hold mosquitoes in high regard.
No matter where you are on the planet,
Mosquitoes are the cause of many problems.
To tell the truth,
It would probably be a good idea for humanity to completely eradicate this insect.
It took 30 years for science to develop the technology at the heart of this factory.
This is a very ingenious process taking place here.
A specific gene is inserted inside a mosquito egg.
This gene forces the larvae to self-destruct.
And this time bomb is contained in each of the eggs that these millions of mosquitoes will produce.
Here we have our dried eggs and the factory produces almost 1000 grams per week.
But how can these mosquitoes reach adulthood if they are born with a gene that destroys them in the larval stage?
The water in which the larvae develop is infused with an antidote that prevents the gene from being triggered.
As long as the mosquitoes remain in the factory,
They are developing normally.
After a few days,
The larvae are separated according to their sex.
The male is smaller.
The female is larger.
Therefore, using a filtration process,
I can sort the males that pass through this filter.
while the females remain trapped.
The females remain at the factory to lay their eggs.
And they need to be fed.
A production line operating day and night is required.
They need 20 liters of blood per day to feed themselves.
The males,
them,
have a different destiny.
The male is released into the wild and all he has to do is find the females and reproduce with them.
This is the primary role of the male.
They will be released into the wild in search of a female.
They will then mate.
But the larvae will not be able to survive.
The male transmits his deadly gene to his offspring.
In a few days,
the gene begins to be expressed.
And since the antidote used in the laboratory cannot be found in nature,
The larvae die.
Deprived of offspring,
The mosquito population is declining rapidly.
but the process must be repeated constantly.
Genetic modification is not the only scientific solution against mosquitoes.
Trials are underway to test the effectiveness of a bacterium called Volbachia,
capable of paralyzing mosquito larvae.
The future of each approach depends greatly on its cost.
Many fear that it will be too expensive for those who need it most.
developing countries.
We must remain very vigilant to ensure that these control methods are affordable for the populations where they will be used.
and especially in the long term.
Will this decrease be permanent?
This is one of the major challenges of these new approaches being proposed for mosquito population control.
No one disputes the need to take strong action against the mosquito.
But the Zika story is far from over.
Even though Zika cases have decreased significantly in South America,
Most experts fear that they will reappear in the coming years.
And on the Brazilian side,
The conclusions of the latest research are even more alarming.
Dr. Brasile...
closely monitors the evolution of the disease across the country.
As labor progressed and the children were born,
We understood that microcephaly was only the tip of the iceberg.
Recent research suggests that many infants born without microcephaly can still develop neurological problems later in life.
There are babies who are born with a normal-sized skull.
But in whom microcephaly develops later.
She then presents with vision deficits,
hearing loss.
NOW,
This is called congenital Zika syndrome.
Brazil has launched a large-scale program to monitor babies born to mothers with Zika.
No one can say how many children will develop neurological complications.
This will take a long time.
Before the experts have any certainties.
These children are growing up and nobody knows how they will develop.
There are also the mothers.
More than 13,000 mothers whose children are affected.
Zika took the world by surprise.
This seemingly harmless virus has long concealed its destructive potential.
It was only after several decades in the shadows that he revealed himself.
Vaccine research is ongoing and may result in success in a few years.
Waiting for,
The fight is focused on mosquitoes, the control of which is becoming increasingly complex and costly.
During this time,
mosquitoes in Hedes, Egypt
them,
are spreading.
EZK is not the only disease they can transmit to us.
There are thousands of other viruses in nature capable of causing more deadly symptoms.
Mosquitoes have already conquered vast territories in Southern Europe and a large part of the United States.
And another species of mosquito,
particularly aggressive,
threat.
What we are witnessing in this cage is a veritable civil war.
which happens on a very fine scale,
but which has global implications for the entire world.
In this cage,
Aedes aegypti is violently attacked by this other species.
Aedes albopictus.
commonly known as the tiger mosquito.
This mosquito is extremely aggressive.
It will compete with other mosquitoes,
with local mosquitoes,
to replace mosquitoes where they are and settle in their place.
In nature,
Albopictus encroaches on the territory of Aedes aegypti.
At first glance,
This seems to be good news.
But this new species likes to feed on the blood of animals.
as much as that of men.
Researchers fear they could transmit a new virus from deep within a distant jungle.
triggering an uncontrollable global epidemic.
There are still many viruses today,
in very remote areas,
in tropical forest regions.
All it would take is for these viruses to leave these forests,
travel,
for an epidemic to break out.
And I would be quite unable to tell you who the next one will be.
Man's long war against the mosquito and the diseases it carries is far from over.